MATEUS M. FURQUIM MENDONCA

Machine Learning and Software Engineer

@ mfurquimdev@gmail.com

mfurquimdev

in/mfurquimdev

mfurquim.dev

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Highly skilled software engineer with over 5 years of experience and a diverse background - encompassing firmware and backend development, as well as DevOps consultancy. Committed to team growth and innovation through effective mentoring and collaboration. Strong problem-solving skills with a passion for delivering high-quality software solutions.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Back-end Developer

DevGrid

□ Jan 2021 - Present

United Kingdom (Remote)

Managed several microservices that employ machine learning algorithms to estimate house appliances' energy consumption.

- Achieved up to 59% improvement in Python write operations on Cassandra through the safe utilization of unlogged batches.
- > Iteratively improved domain models following Domain Driven Design approach, increasing efficiency in delivering new features.

Embedded Software Developer

Autotrac

Brasilia, DF - Brazil

Maintained security and logistic features of an embedded system for a customized hardware and Linux kernel.

- Employed dependency injection and other SOLID principles to enhance C++ code quality and maintainability.
- Implemented robust monitoring solutions to gather real-time performance data, ensuring optimal system efficiency and responsiveness.

DevOps Consultant

IBM

[™] Jan 2019 - Nov 2019

Brasilia, DF - Brazil

Collaborated with multiple teams to improve observability of the back-end services of a prominent banking institution.

- > Contributed to self-discovering services feature by utilizing the etcd key-value store, consistent hashing and a federation of Prometheus.
- > Employed PromQL to develop alerts that detected low performance of new deployments and potential DDoS attacks.

INTERN EXPERIENCE

Security Software Researcher

[™] Nov 2015 - Jul 2016

LADES at UnB

Brasilia. DF - Brazil

Enhanced an Intrusion Detection System with unsupervised machine learning to strengthen the security measures of the Brazilian Army.

- > Configured a **Debian** server to capture all network packets in promiscuous mode using Wireshark and replay them in a controlled environment.
- Successfully detected masked malicious network packets using K-Means clustering algorithm and distributed processing with **Spark** and **Hadoop**.

Software Engineer Intern

iii Jan 2015 - Apr 2015

CanAssist at UVic

Victoria, BC - Canada

Developed an elderly care embedded system which notifies relatives in case of emergency.

- > Devised an automated data-driven regression testing methodology, improving the efficiency of the testing cycle and ensuring alignment with requirements.
- > Accomplished a low resource consumption of Raspberry Pi by rotating log using the C/C++ language and the Qt Framework.

EDUCATION

Machine Learning DevOps Engineer

Udacity

Online

BEng. Software Engineering

Universidade de Brasilia (UnB)

Prasilia, DF - Brazil iii Mar 2011 - Jul 2017

University of Victoria (UVic)

LANGUAGES

Portuguese	Mother Tongue
English	Fluent
Python	Working Knowledge
C/C++	Working Knowledge
Rust	Basic Knowledge

















Made with LATEX